<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Reviews &#8211; Terry Plays</title>
	<atom:link href="category/review/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Game ideas, lame ideas, and more</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 15:44:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Promised Neverland was lame from the start</title>
		<link>/2021/12/07/the-promised-neverland-was-lame-from-the-start/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[terrytorres]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 04:09:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[anime]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lame]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[overrated]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[promised neverland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[review]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://terry-torres.com/plays/?p=213</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In episode 1, Norman and Emma find Conny&#8217;s plush toy, Little Bunny™. It appears Conny had forgotten it while she was whisked away from the orphanage to her new adoptive family. Conny might still be at the tunnel that acts as the only exit from the property they live on, so Norman and Emma rush&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="2021/12/07/the-promised-neverland-was-lame-from-the-start/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">The Promised Neverland was lame from the start</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" width="411" height="153" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/pormised-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-248" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/pormised-1.jpg 411w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/12/pormised-1-300x112.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 411px) 100vw, 411px" /></figure></div>



<p>In episode 1, Norman and Emma find Conny&#8217;s plush toy, Little Bunny<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />. It appears Conny had forgotten it while she was whisked away from the orphanage to her new adoptive family. Conny might still be at the tunnel that acts as the only exit from the property they live on, so Norman and Emma rush to deliver the toy.</p>



<p>They discover Conny&#8217;s corpse inauspiciously splayed out in the bed of a truck. I had the thought, &#8220;If I were trafficking children for secret and nefarious means, I might make a point of murdering them after the gate they had just passed through had been closed shut to prevent witnesses or escape. But maybe I&#8217;m overthinking this.&#8221;</p>



<span id="more-213"></span>



<p>Norman and Emma hear someone approaching and hide under the truck. Soon, the orphanage caretaker appears, along with a set of demons, who discuss the details of raising and killing children with the intent of feeding them to demons of high status. They take Conny&#8217;s body off of the truck and put it in a special container of blue liquid.</p>



<p>I had the thought, &#8220;Why do the steps of this process appear to be killing the child, putting them onto a truck, and then taking them off of the truck to put into a special container, only to put them back onto the truck again? Why not complete the entire process in one of the smaller rooms connected to this tunnel? But maybe I&#8217;m overthinking this.&#8221;</p>



<p>One of the demons seems to smell something – apparently the rich scent of edible children – and slowly moves toward the truck. On peeking beneath it, the demon finds nothing. Cut to: Norman and Emma running out into the field between the exit tunnel and the orphanage, catching their breath.</p>



<p>I had the thought, &#8220;If I were one of four tall creatures in the midst of completing a secret transaction, I feel I would be easily able to see and hear anyone leaving the immediate area, especially if it&#8217;s a tunnel with only a single viable exit. But maybe I&#8217;m overthinking it. Moreover, maybe this just isn&#8217;t a story that focuses on the logistics of this fictional world and the specific consequences of which character performs what action in which location. Maybe it&#8217;s more about thematic exploration of the pains of growing up, and the moment-to-moment emotional conflict between characters.</p>



<p>A moment later, Mom, the caretaker of the orphanage, is shown having found Little Bunny<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />, meaning she knows that there were witnesses to the demonic child food transaction. I had the thought, &#8220;Oh. I guess this is a story that focuses on the logistics of the world and the specific consequences of characters&#8217; actions. But only when they&#8217;re leaving behind stuffed animals, not when they&#8217;re escaping demons from closed quarters and their life is in immediate danger.&#8221;</p>



<p>To the show&#8217;s credit, I wanted to keep watching even as I saw the cracks in the foundation. It has the attractive quality of many mediocre anime: the anticipation of seeing a unique world presented visually with as much detail as you could conjure in your own imagination. Many anime have been viewed to completion with the faint hope that they could possibly live up to the expectations of their high concept.</p>



<p>Much as Mom successfully mimics a caring mother, Neverland&#8217;s imitations of a genuine thriller are often effective. The immediate challenges the children are presented with – having to devise an escape while their enemy is closing in on them – offer tantalizing opportunities for dramatic, high-stakes situations that could lead to trauma and death for any of the children. Soon after, the orphanage welcomes another child – reminding us that the orphanage has a schedule that will soon claim yet another life – as well as another devious adult, doubling the threat to their secret plans. It&#8217;s a perfect opportunity for the viewer and the children to start on the same page and begin strategizing an escape.</p>



<p>Unfortunately, the subsequent pages become by turns less scrutable and more pedantic. Our heroes quickly discover the tall wall around their property and decide climbing it is the best method of escape. They cleverly decide that the best way to train their friends to run and climb the wall is to play Tag competitively. This in turns lead to the new adult, Sister, participating in the game and showing the sheer power an adult can have over even the quickest children.</p>



<p>But alongside the training, the focus of our heroes&#8217; investigation are often strange or unfounded. An inordinate amount of time is spent on divining the logistics of the tracking devices implanted into each child, where they are, and how they can be removed or deactivated. In real life, this would be an important consideration for an escape, but it&#8217;s a strange focus within a constructed narrative. Ray reveals that he has a plan to deactivate these trackers. Norman and Emma do not push for more information, and then he fails to elaborate for multiple episodes. The existence of tracking devices are neither the most illuminating bit of world-building nor the most obvious obstacle to the escape plan. They haven&#8217;t actually made sure they can even escape, but they&#8217;ve jumped ahead to what may happen if they do.</p>



<p>Another cul de sac for the investigation involves the discovery of &#8220;property of&#8221; labels inside various books that have been donated to the orphanage&#8217;s library. These labels have secret Morse code messages. When decoded, random nouns are revealed: farm, monster, promise. They seem to have been donated for the expressed purpose of letting the children know that they have an ally on the outside – only actually useful if the children have already discovered the orphanage&#8217;s secret for themselves.</p>



<p>While watching these scenes play out, I began the work of thinking like a character living in this world. For example, if I&#8217;m a caretaker of a demonic orphanage, why would I have any books from the outside world at all? Aside from being an obvious method of distributing messages from the outside world, it provides the children with expectations of future lives they can plan for. Books are needless vectors for instilling hope. Any child that was given dreams for their own future by reading these books might become radicalized if they were to stumble upon the truth in the open back of my delivery truck, and then plan an escape, threatening my livelihood.</p>



<p>If I did need a demonic library in my child farm, I would only stock it with demonic propaganda. In fact, I wouldn&#8217;t keep anything secret at all. I would raise the children from birth to be extremely excited to grow up and be a wonderful offering to the great Demon King. I would frame their entire existence as a journey toward becoming the happiest and smartest little child any demon has ever eaten. I might even give fake history lessons every day to make this fantasy more believable and palatable. My whole strategy would be devoted to making sure they never even dream of escape.</p>



<p>Curiously, Mom is never seen giving school lessons to the children. It could be that their education is more experimental and self-guided. I would think that, except that their education seems entirely devoted to taking standardized tests. These tests are taken on digital apparatuses, requiring the children to interact with screens, headphones, and barcode readers. This is the only modern technology the children are ever seen using, making the testing process extremely strange and conspicuous. The children&#8217;s entire worth is based on their test scores. The greatest indicator that a child&#8217;s life is soon coming to an end is their test score.</p>



<p>A perfectly natural question occurred to me: What is up with these tests? What is in them? What do they measure? How can they be used as a tool by our heroes to divine what demons think is important about children? I anticipated the next scene in which the children would take their test. I wanted to see how our heroes would react differently during a tense testing session now that they knew the truth of their purpose, or if any clues were discovered in the test questions.</p>



<p>I was extremely hung up on these tests because they seemed like such an obvious avenue for social commentary. A standardized test deciding how soon a child will be discarded from society or consumed by it? Perfect. It&#8217;s just the edge a story like this needs. Otherwise, what is this story about? It can&#8217;t just be, &#8220;Wouldn&#8217;t it be fucked up if an orphanage was actually a farm for demon food?&#8221;</p>



<p>We never see the children take the tests again. It truly seems the presence of these standardized tests are meant to make one thing certain: our main characters are geniuses. They have the documentation to prove it. This story, in fact, holds that standardized tests, demonic or not, are an efficient way to measure one&#8217;s intelligence, their juicy brains, and their value by extension.</p>



<p>A genius mind is indeed highly valued in this world, and is also the most common trait in our main cast. Norman and Ray continually pursue even the most inane line of thinking as close to its conclusion as possible, easily filling in gaps with wisdom received from reading books far beyond their age level, casually dismissing plans or hypotheses they deem improbable. Norman is a genius who attempts to be kind. Ray is a genius who is intensely cynical. Emma is mostly just naive, and exists for the others to explain things too – or she should, but her absence doesn&#8217;t stop them from explaining things to each other.</p>



<p>A story set in an orphanage where children grow up close together begs for a colorful ensemble, but even the main three characters come up sepia, with barely enough personality to split between them. Their conversations mostly have two rhythms: Ray and Norman consider a plan, and then one of them just does it; or, Ray and Norman consider a plan, Ray introduces an inhumane or misanthropic option, Emma rejects it, and Norman convinces Ray to go with the humane option. Up until the end, no one is forced to change the way they think.</p>



<p>You can imagine then how the rest of the cast fares. Most of the children aren&#8217;t named, and many of them don&#8217;t have enough funds to stay on model. The main trio do induct two other members to their team, Don &amp; Gilda. They each have one personality trait, one being brash and one being timid, but ironically they are a welcome presence in the cast because their childish faults contrast so much with the mature genius of our heroes.</p>



<p>The story seems to hold their normal-ness against them, as scenes often refuse Don &amp; Gilda&#8217;s presence. On more than one occasion they just sort of excuse themselves from a room so the three mains can mope about something. On more than one occasion, our heroes devise a plan that involve splitting into two groups: Ray, Norman, and Emma in one group, Don and Gilda in the other. In another ensemble show, opportunities might be taken to pair together different characters with different personalities in different situations and show how they each might influence the other&#8217;s values and view of the world, to challenge their assumptions and grow their relationship, or ignite emotional conflict.</p>



<p>Time and again, Neverland proves that it&#8217;s not interested in emotional conflict, or really any conflict, as much as stuff happening, or the hypothetical threat that stuff may happen. It&#8217;s less a story about how people suffer consequences from their behavior, and more about how actions have reactions. Less about how a decision might lead to regret, and more about how a ball will roll if you nudge it.</p>



<p>What will happen if one of the adults joins a game of Tag with the children? Well, they&#8217;ll mostly just end up playing Tag. What will happen if a spy is discovered in the group? Well, the spy will agree to work with them. What will happen if Mom corners them in her secret lair? Well, they&#8217;ll just escape during a cutaway. And what will happen if Mom sneaks up on them in the woods while they&#8217;re holding the rope they spent so long gathering the fabric to make? Well, they&#8217;ll just chuck it deeper into the woods. The children never really suffer setbacks to their plans, just brief interruptions. Neverland does attempt to mimic a true consequence in a classically dumb way, by giving two of our heroes battle scars, but dramatic tension goes slack when it becomes immediately apparent that at least half of those wounds were completely gratuitous.</p>



<p>Neverland spends so much time avoiding emotional growth and grappling with each character&#8217;s ideologies so it can instead just set up some dominoes with the intent of knocking them over. And even after including so much prattling about hypothetical scenarios from alienating wunderkinds, genius is almost never a vital component to the action. It doesn&#8217;t take an Einstein to lie about the location of a bag of rope, or to hide that bag in a bush. To be clear, in the end, their final escape plan is to 1) light a fire and 2) run away.</p>



<p>This scheming goes from disappointing to just pointless when you step back and realize just how incredibly lazy their antagonist is. As a reminder, Mom is assigned as the caretaker of the single most valuable child farm in the demonic world. And this is not a part-time gig. Rearing and containing these children is her sole responsibility.  She has a child tracking monitor on her person at all times. The children never think to steal it or replace it with something else, because the fact that she simply forgets to look at it for long periods of time is basically the key to their entire plan. She routinely avoids checking it when our heroes are surveying the perimeter wall. She routinely avoids checking it (or apparently just looking out the window) when the children&#8217;s training escalates from games of Tag to explicitly building and using zip-lines to cross a great distance. She correctly surmises that her temporary assistant, Sister, is attempting to betray her, but rather than manipulate her with a promise of a promotion (something easily within her power), she plots her death, and then fails to hire a replacement, giving up her greatest advantage. Again: all while knowing that an escape plan is being devised. The children are also responsible for cooking and cleaning apparently, so what the hell does Mom do all day? Aside from act as a perfect distillation of the incompetence of the managerial class.</p>



<p>(Really, why kill Sister at all? Sister believes she can expose Mom&#8217;s failure to adhere to protocol and steal the prestigious position of caretaker for herself. However, Grandma, the head honcho, conspires with Mom to kill Sister. So if Mom is already a star employee and Grandma is on Mom&#8217;s side, Sister has no leverage over Mom. So how is Sister a threat? How is she more valuable dead than alive? Her death makes more sense as a shocking moment in the middle of the season to stave accusations that nothing important is happening.)</p>



<p>Despite being very stupid, Mom is close to being the most interesting character because of her background, at first strongly hinted at and then outright presented, as a potential child meal herself who was then steered toward a leadership training course that ultimately led to her position as a caretaker. We see how she was incentivized to uphold this cruel system for her own safety, and eventually as a misguided way to give the children happiness prior to their deaths. We are finally, finally shown a long-lasting consequence of living in this fictional world that poses the uncomfortable yet relatable question of what it is that we force others to sacrifice for our own comfort.</p>



<p>Oh, accept that we already saw this same backstory when Sister died. Once again, Mom is too slow to make a difference.</p>



<p>In the end, it&#8217;s unclear what the point of it all is. The innate spark of hope in all children is the best tool for survival in a cruel world? No, all the children who act like children are just led around by mature super geniuses who make a point of not thinking or speaking like children. Childish innocence must be shed to survive in a cruel world? No, their first plan to escape death with all of their friends was framed as naive, but then that&#8217;s exactly what they did. That it would be fucked up if an orphanage was a child farm for demons?</p>



<p>Well&#8230; not even that, really. After the very beginning, threats to the children fade to the background. The children learn everything they need to escape in their own library, and they constantly break curfew and get into screaming matches and no one ever cares. One lesson you can take away from Neverland is that it&#8217;s good to have a stunning intellect or great athleticism, but it&#8217;s even better to retain all of your memories from when you were a fetus.</p>



<p>If you like the threat of death hanging over childhood friends as they seek to understand and escape a strange and cruel world, instead consider:</p>



<p><a href="https://www.goodsmile.info/en/product/4432/figma+Levi+Cleaning+ver.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Attack on Titan</a><br><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WtWiMTDhCUo" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">From the New World</a><br><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kqBNQEUI8dM" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Made in Abyss</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>So I played The Witcher 3: Wild Hunt</title>
		<link>/2020/06/29/so-i-played-the-witcher-3-wild-hunt/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[terrytorres]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 15:25:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://terry-torres.com/plays/?p=180</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Lauren and I finally wrapped up our biggest game of the social distancing era, The Witcher 3: Wild Hunt: Complete Edition. I do not really understand why it&#8217;s considered the greatest game of all time. It&#8217;s like a mix between a Zelda game and an Elder Scrolls game, and it doesn&#8217;t get either quite right.&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="2020/06/29/so-i-played-the-witcher-3-wild-hunt/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">So I played The Witcher 3: Wild Hunt</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Lauren and I finally wrapped up our biggest game of the social distancing era, The Witcher 3: Wild Hunt: Complete Edition. I do not really understand why it&#8217;s considered the greatest game of all time. It&#8217;s like a mix between a Zelda game and an Elder Scrolls game, and it doesn&#8217;t get either quite right. Movement and combat always feels just slightly delayed, the choices that are allowed don&#8217;t offer for much role-playing or especially emergent storytelling, and considering how much time is spent managing inventory, there is a lot of lag simply navigating the many menus. Although it&#8217;s fun to arrange abilities and buffs in such a way to maximize your potential, It never FEELS especially good to play, at least compared to other Games of the Year.</p>



<p>I get why anyone would like it though &#8211; it&#8217;s freaking huge. It&#8217;s full of stuff. The sheer amount of writing and recorded audio even for the most insignificant situations is unbelievable. And the accessibility to all the quests is like nothing I&#8217;ve seen. You can find out about a quest by overhearing a conversation, pulling a notice off of a bulletin board, meeting the quest-giver in town, or just by running into the abandoned house they were going to ask you to look at anyway. It doesn&#8217;t always feel like a well-crafted game, but it is clearly the result of a lot of work. Sometimes it pays off, but honestly, it&#8217;s just too much.</p>



<p>We were told we could jump into this one without playing the previous entries, which now feels like a lie. Most of the main storyline lacks urgency because we never felt a deep connection to the major players, and the big threats are&#8230; pretty lame, predictable villains. Frankly, most of the major events felt BYOC (bring your own charm) because the characters left theirs in the previous games.</p>



<p>Thankfully, we stuck with it to get to the DLC expansions, Hearts of Stone and Blood &amp; Wine, which were, frankly, what I was hoping the rest of the game would be like. It felt a lot like we were playing through the early kitschy seasons of a TV show (say, Buffy the Vampire Slayer) to get to the later, wilder, genre-pushing seasons. A lot more fun, a lot more imagination, a lot more unique boss fights (though, again, it&#8217;s rough fighting a Zelda-style boss fight without Zelda-style responsive control). Also, the Witcher acts more like a professional rolling into town and resolving magically-complicated Shakespearean family power struggles and not some dumbass on a wild (goose) hunt.</p>



<p>The disparate feelings between the main game and the expanded content felt like a natural result of the production. This game is huge and, like most games this size, required a huge crunch to be finished. The result is a game that usually feels spread thin. The reason the DLC feels so much more lively is likely just a result of more people focusing on a smaller set of stories. Seems like a much better use of resources! As is, this game is overwhelming to the point I really can&#8217;t imagine returning to it.</p>



<p>Still, it&#8217;s hard not to spend so much time with something and not feel an attachment. With our last quest finished, we had Geralt strip down to his underwear, hang up his best suit of armor to display, down 20 bottles of wine (and a few onions by accident), read a goodbye note from an old vampire friend, and hit the hay in his retirement vineyard. Goodnight, Geralt.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="The Witcher 3: Wild Hunt – Goodnight, Geralt" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kvHbnk8Vs5U?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What I get and did not get from NieR: Automata</title>
		<link>/2017/09/20/what-i-get-and-did-not-get-from-nier-automata/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[terrytorres]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 02:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://terry-torres.com/plays/?p=175</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I get&#160;the sensation of being a well-built killing machine refined from millennia worth of war data. The slashing, shooting, and dodging come from the previous NieR, but these actions are amped up in every way, bigger, faster, and most importantly, effortless. You don’t even have to hold your weapons most of the time! I did&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="2017/09/20/what-i-get-and-did-not-get-from-nier-automata/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">What I get and did not get from NieR: Automata</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>I get</strong>&nbsp;the sensation of being a well-built killing machine refined from millennia worth of war data. The slashing, shooting, and dodging come from the previous NieR, but these actions are amped up in every way, bigger, faster, and most importantly, effortless. You don’t even have to hold your weapons most of the time!</p>



<p><strong>I did not get</strong>&nbsp;the point of making the differences between each difficulty level so severe. Easy mode is basically meant to allow you to experience the story without much heartache. Normal mode is meant to be just challenging enough to make the proceedings feel dramatic without being punishing, but most difficulties can be solved by just… using a healing item when your HP get low, and failure usually comes less often from a desperate struggle than being too lazy to pull out a Medium Recovery in time. Hard mode decides to pair harder-hitting enemies with the inability to even lock on to them — TWO new challenges to get used to! The wish for a mode between Normal and Hard meant a constant feeling that there was some alternate version of the game that I’d rather play.</p>



<p><strong>I get</strong>&nbsp;the feeling that chips and their customization were meant to be the central mechanic of the game, or should have been. They offer the clearest encouragement to pay attention to the way you play, either enticing you toward different strategies or allowing to you make your current methods even more effective through the clever combination of fusion of the right chips. They’re also a constant reminder that you are not human, driven home brilliantly by the fact that your entire chip set is customizable<em>&nbsp;except for your core processor</em>, which you need to literally function.</p>



<p><strong>I don’t get</strong>&nbsp;why chips are sidelined by less interesting mechanics, specifically the acquisition and equipment of multiple weapons. I changed up my weapon sets at maybe two points in the game, but I’m sure I wouldn’t have had a problem with using only the first two swords the whole time. I’ll grant that different weapon choices can provide different tactical advantages — this is especially true when countering after a dodge can result in a rising slash, a spinning attack, or a forward thrust — but there isn’t enough motivation to try even half of the 38 weapons you can get. I would rather have had twice as meant chip sets as they provide, and I would have MUCH rather had the option to switch between chip sets from the quick menu instead of weapon sets!</p>



<p><strong>I get&nbsp;</strong>the world design. The best way to illustrate a foot soldier’s part in a global conflict without actually bringing the globe into it is to give them dominion over a large contained area filled with distinct zones. The “ruined city” and its neighbors can either represent to the entire world, or just one apparently very important metropolis. This “anywhere”-ness accentuates the distant, fable-like tone of the game. The minimalism of the game’s style helps there, as well. Though tying your narrative to a mostly empty world populated by featureless automatons probably made the producers happy. *taps nose twice*</p>



<p><strong>I get</strong>&nbsp;the side quests. In the last NieR, sidequests were an absolute nuisance that padded out the game and got in the way of the story. In Automata, the side quests, justified as operations to assist the android Resistance and gather intelligence on the machine threat, ARE the story. The simple act of being on Earth and being sentient — being alive — makes machines act strangely, and the game shows basically every possible permutation of ageless, disaffected robots looking for purpose. We see machines love each other, hate each other, try to be human, try to be BETTER than human, embrace struggle, find out what it means to live, what it means to&nbsp;<em>be.&nbsp;</em>Most define themselves by a single trait — the way most NPCs tend to do, right — and either embrace or are trapped by it. They so often act like any quest givers in any video game, but by merely knowing that their identities and desires originate from an entirely artificial place, your decision to take on these missions means elevating the stakes of their pantomime and recognizing their will, in turn&nbsp;<em>asserting that everything is meaningless until you provide meaning to it.</em>&nbsp;Magnifying this sensation is the ever-present irony that the self-serious androids, despite looking human, make far fewer attempts at acting human than most machines you meet. This is what it really means to ask the question, “What is it to be human?” This is truly science fiction.</p>



<p><strong>I get</strong>&nbsp;the abstraction of time, kind of. It’s unclear how much time passes over the course of the game, especially when you take on sidequests that cut to a title reading TWO DAYS LATER once in a while, but it’s long enough to feel like an active and momentous number of weeks — months? — in the war against the machine threat, and long enough for 2B and 9S to form a working relationship.</p>



<p>That said,&nbsp;<strong>I don’t get</strong>&nbsp;the relationship between 2B and 9S. 2B is cold and 9S is outgoing, right? That comes across very effectively in the way they work together. 9S not only does most of the talking between the two of them, he also does most of the talking to NPCs on behalf of the both of them, not just because he’s naturally a talker, but because 2B either comes to expect this of him or allows him to. Their closeness is most believable in the subtle transition after a number of missions, when they go from clashing with each other to becoming comfortable in their complimentary roles.</p>



<p>That is, until their roles get switched up seemingly at random. They have a bad habit of mixing up their “machine’s have wills and are interesting” / “machines have no wills and must die” routine whenever they come across a new set of strange robots, with 9S being pretty inconsistent. 9S is the older model, yet he needs to be reminded that emotions are prohibited by YoRHA. And then 2B seems to forget about the emotion prohibition, and is even the first to shed tears! I get the change that’s being illustrated here, with the cold soldier getting in touch with her feelings, but there is basically no proper set-up for this moment. That is, unless you assume that she learned the value of caring for others from the sidequests you complete, which passes the work of convincing the audience that 2B and 9S have a reason for caring about each other onto the audience itself.</p>



<p>Actually, this is the abstraction of time coming back to bite us in the ass. Relationships presented between NPCs are suggested to have endured for centuries, but we’re supposed to believe that these taciturn androids are soul mates after… what, a month?</p>



<p>So<strong>&nbsp;I don’t really get</strong>&nbsp;where 9S’ enduring affection for 2B comes from, but&nbsp;<strong>I sort of do get</strong>&nbsp;that his obsession with the loss of 2B is meant to be analogous to his loss of purpose as her supporter, a member of YoRHA, and a defender of humanity when the shit hits the fan at the top of act three.</p>



<p><strong>I don’t get</strong>&nbsp;A2. The most interesting possibility in the discovery of A2 is that there is a powerful android who lives off the grid who might be able to able to provide a new perspective into YoRHA’s real workings. Instead A2 is just like… a tough loner, and that’s it. It’s not even clear what her deal is unless you gather intelligence documents to reveal that she was an older model sent on a previous secret mission by YoRHA, which you… basically already know before you play as her.</p>



<p>Her ultimate purpose is to represent the desire of living for living’s sake in contrast to 9S’ madness-induced nihilism at the climax, but the path feels clumsy. Wasn’t there some other way to have this emotional moment? Why couldn’t the story be constructed so that 2B an 9S were facing each other in the end, and have their point of contention be disagreeing on what to do with the information that humanity is extinct?</p>



<p><strong>I get that</strong>&nbsp;the game wants to shake things up once in a while by having you control different characters. It does this pretty well, most notably with the little machine getting oil for its “big brother” at the start of 9S’s story, an especially brutal moment when you trip and spill it everywhere. It really helps you understand the stark difference between the effortless flow of the androids and the ponderous gesticulating of the machines.</p>



<p><strong>I don’t get</strong>&nbsp;2B actually being 2E. I have no idea if that news is meant to momentous or not. If 2B’s whole thing was making sure 9S never got to the truth, what circumstances decide whether she is cold and dutiful about it or emotional and remorseful about it? Has this cycle repeated outside of the game as played? Moreover, the shallow “gotcha” of 2B’s identity switcharoo undermines 9S’ decisions to keep the truth of humanity’s extinction from 2B. Which sounds like a more interesting secret: the beliefs of every sentient thing on Earth are based on a lie, or “Actually, it was a different letter”?</p>



<p><strong>I don’t get</strong>&nbsp;why Project YoRHA is designed to end the way it does. Considering the purpose of its formation — to boost android morale, a nebulous concept; why not just… program androids that have morale? — why violently end something that was fake, anyway? To hide its existence from who? The machine network’s purpose for fighting continuously — so it can evolve — makes more sense in comparison. But what does creating and destroying a military force actually&nbsp;<em>do</em>&nbsp;for humanity’s memory?</p>



<p><strong>I do get</strong>&nbsp;the repetition of ironic circumstances of origin and the maddening implications of being created in the image of another and being forced to rely on that other. It happens first and most obviously with Adam and Eve, the game using the names of the first biblical humans to make it VERY CLEAR that one is derived from the other. But it happens again when you meet A2, the Adam to 2B’s Eve, and in a way it happens again in reverse, when 2B passes on her sword with her data to A2. And it happens&nbsp;<em>again</em>, most saliently, when 9S discovers that YoRHA’s black boxes are based on the same technology as the cores of machines. Not only does YoRHA as an organization exist because of the machines, but, literally, members of YoRHA can only exist because of the machines. This irony is the core of the absurdity of all conflict.</p>



<p><strong>I don’t get&nbsp;</strong>the obsession with repetition and multiple endings. What if instead of being split into multiple playthroughs, the game was just… the game? And then there were just two endings: A2’s and 9S’. After all, those are the only endings that require a choice tobe made, while the ones before that happen as a matter of course.</p>



<p>If you are going to have multiple playthroughs,&nbsp;<strong>I don’t get</strong>&nbsp;why you would spoil the future ones. After playing as 9S, I assumed that the next playthrough would be as A2 — an easy assumption to make since you spend two playthroughs picking up Taunt chips you can’t use. I was so surprised to see that the third playthrough didn’t go back in time, but forward!</p>



<p>… Is what I would say if the second playthrough didn’t end with a teaser for what happens in the third playthrough. The one I was… about to play. Why would they do that?</p>



<p>Now,&nbsp;<strong>I do get</strong>&nbsp;one part about the second playthrough: being on the other side of 2B’s reboot after the first mission and watching yourself from the first playthrough make your configurations. The sensation that I was watching and BEING watched in that way felt like a very personal moment, and was the perfect way to get across the feeling of being connected to someone else. That felt like a door was opening onto the possibilities of seeing the same story from a different angle. There should have been more of those moments.</p>



<p>The only other moment that matches, and exceeds, the success of that one is, of course, ending E.</p>



<p>One of the great ironies of Automata is that the least humanoid characters are the ones to exhibit the greatest humanity (that is, the belief that life is worth living regardless of its purpose). That the belief that 2B, 9S, and A2 have a right to live comes from 2B’s support pod, the most primitive of all the artificial beings you ever meet — and that it’s able to awaken to this will over the course of the third act just by&nbsp;<em>talking and learning to understand somebody else</em>&nbsp;— is such a beautiful notion that I want to cry just thinking about it. (That said,&nbsp;<strong>I don’t get</strong>&nbsp;why the pods being the moral center of the story isn’t set up earlier; it could’ve been a great bookend).</p>



<p>Being in a bullet hell battle with the credits is goofy at first (I mean, Smash Bros. did this in ’98) until&nbsp;<strong>you get</strong>&nbsp;that you are literally fighting the concept of Ending. And&nbsp;<strong>I get</strong>&nbsp;the concept of your friends lending you their Friend Energy has been applied in every anime or anime-adjacent story from Dragonball to Persona. But other people who’ve played the game cheering you on from all over the world and then joining your game to die for you as the song swells in multiple languages feels like a completely unique experience in the moment.</p>



<p>And the notion that this game, a follow-up to a game that was already bleak, turned out to be even more bleak for most of its playtime, then flips it around to being happy and culminates in asking you to be part of something huge by giving up your save data to help someone you’ll never meet, an act that in the moment feels more like a gift than a sacrifice…&nbsp;<strong>I get that</strong>.</p>



<p><strong>I get that</strong>&nbsp;finding meaning in life is recognizing and caring for the life of someone else.</p>



<p><strong>I get that</strong>&nbsp;Automata tells clear, ringing truths by using its game mechanics to drive the story.&nbsp;<strong>I get that</strong>&nbsp;its points are muddled, hollowed, and prone to “anime logic” when using only its script to tell the story.&nbsp;<strong>I get that</strong>&nbsp;Automata’s best moments are playable.&nbsp;<strong>I get that</strong>&nbsp;its worst moments are not.</p>



<p><strong>I don’t get&nbsp;</strong>a lot of the game’s trappings.&nbsp;<strong>I don’t get</strong>&nbsp;wanting to reach a broad audience while always conveying the sensation that you missed something by not playing the first NieR.&nbsp;<strong>I don’t get</strong>&nbsp;combining action and RPG mechanics until each ultimately diffuses the effectiveness of the other.&nbsp;<strong>I don’t&nbsp;<em>really&nbsp;</em>get</strong>&nbsp;the plot’s layered double-crossings and obfuscations of motivation that still manage to leave emotional moments in cutscenes feeling unclear or unearned.</p>



<p>Despite that,&nbsp;<strong>I get</strong>&nbsp;the feeling that Automata knows what its purpose is, which seems to be the point.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" width="474" height="267" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/1_xNrZZkEyqaRv4Vc_vXu1HQ.png" alt="" class="wp-image-176" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/1_xNrZZkEyqaRv4Vc_vXu1HQ.png 474w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/06/1_xNrZZkEyqaRv4Vc_vXu1HQ-300x169.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 474px) 100vw, 474px" /></figure></div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lame shit in Persona 5 that could have been fixed</title>
		<link>/2017/06/16/lame-shit-in-persona-5-that-could-have-been-fixed/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[terrytorres]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 02:14:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://terry-torres.com/plays/?p=170</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ryuji should have been tempted by fame, and suffered for it.&#160;He is the one character most vocal about unfairness. Not injustice, but unfairness — a purer, more childlish notion that you deserve something for your troubles. He is the party member most bothered by his negative public image. He aches to be recognized for his&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="2017/06/16/lame-shit-in-persona-5-that-could-have-been-fixed/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Lame shit in Persona 5 that could have been fixed</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Ryuji should have been tempted by fame, and suffered for it.</strong>&nbsp;He is the one character most vocal about unfairness. Not injustice, but unfairness — a purer, more childlish notion that you deserve something for your troubles. He is the party member most bothered by his negative public image. He aches to be recognized for his efforts, but knows he has to keep his identity secret. This should have made him completely buy into the hype of the Phantom Thieves’ authority, thirsting for approval from the online fans, excited to give them what they want. Ryuji should have been radicalized to the point of believing that the Phantom Thieves had the vision to be the rightful judge, jury, and executioner of Japan.</p>



<p>Imagine in one of the scenes following Okumura’s death if Ryuji leaned back in one of the booths at Leblanc and said, “Maybe he deserved to die.” Sparks fly as the rest of the group try to counter, forcing themselves to ask what their goal in the end really is.</p>



<p>Of course, Ryuji wouldn’t think he’s being ridiculous — he just believes in the mission more than everyone else. It would be up to the player to decide if Ryuji’s thinking makes him a liability to the team. This could make an interesting twist when we get to the end of Shido’s dungeon, when Ryuji makes his suicide run, a decision he makes not just because he can run good or whatever, but because he’s already shown to believe that, in pursuing the Phantom Thieves’ goals, death is acceptable, even his own.</p>



<p>And then Ryuji should actually die. No lame pointless fake-outs. Make the player wonder if Ryuji’s radicalism was foolish (because it killed him) or noble (because it saved everyone else).</p>



<p>This idea of the Phantom Thieves investing too heavily into their own image is only barely explored in Mishima’s confidant story, to no great effect.</p>



<p><strong>Morgana should have been the Grail’s creation, not Igor’s.</strong>&nbsp;Discovering that he is made by Igor reveals Morgana’s nightmares to be, really,&nbsp;<em>just</em>&nbsp;nightmares, and that his insecurities were actually nothing at all to worry about. This… isn’t dramatic. Instead, Morgana should have been sent by the Grail to mislead the player. However, much as the Grail was distorted by human cognition, Morgana would have been changed by the player’s, but in this case, reformed, becoming an agent for self-determination. This fits perfectly with the game’s theme of rebelling and defying expectations. This would make Morgana a character. As is, he’s reduced to an inefficient&nbsp;<em>deus ex machina</em>.</p>



<p><strong>Ann should have been smarter, more autonomous, and, generally, better respected by the script.</strong>&nbsp;Ann has several lines expressing her dissatisfaction with her catsuit. That doesn’t even make any fucking sense. Why, in a world formed by one’s vision of their self, would she end up with an outfit she doesn’t even like? Let the woman just like being herself, for fuck’s sake.</p>



<p>She’s a professional model, the only member of the group to have a job, and to routinely interact with adults — the very adults so often maligned by this game! She should have maturity and insight that the other character have yet to develop. It doesn’t matter if she isn’t a top student or hacker. Ann shouldn’t be oblivious, she should be smart, and if she’s insecure about anything it makes no sense for it to be her body!</p>



<p>Let’s take that&nbsp;<em>stupid ass scene where she’s asked to pose nude</em>. What would be funnier? If she waved her arms and said, “You want to do WHAAAT?” or if she said, “I always told myself that if I had to pose nude… it wouldn’t be for less than a 200,00 yen.” Exclamation points shoot up over everyone else’s heads. Giving Ann conviction like this gives you so many options when she finally meets up with Yusuke. For example:</p>



<ol><li>She shows up and immediately throw around her weight as a professional model, making increasingly more ridiculous demands for her comfort. Yusuke, obsessed with the creative process, rationalizes her demands as being for the sake of ART, expounding on his own process.</li><li>When asked to disrobe, she makes a big striptease out of it, coming onto Yusuke hard in attempt to turn him on so much that he has to get up and leave, giving her a chance to snoop.</li><li>Like 2, except it’s revealed that Yusuke is completely cold to her advances, asking that she speed things up a little. Realizing she’s in over her head, she just knocks some paint over and says, “Whoops,” forcing him to clean it up while she snoops.</li></ol>



<p>There are bits like this throughout that script that could be tweaked. Don’t let stuff&nbsp;<em>happen</em>&nbsp;to Ann, let her&nbsp;<em>do</em>&nbsp;stuff.</p>



<p><strong>Yusuke should have been fragile, not bombastic.</strong>&nbsp;Yusuke is like the Shylock of Persona characters — potentially interesting, but fucking broken by virtue of being, uh, p r o b l e m a t i c. His&nbsp;<a href="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Monkey%20Cheese" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">monkey cheese</a>&nbsp;antics set him up to be a fan favorite, but it’s all blighted by his entire introductory arc — his treatment of Ann and his static inner motivation of Doing Art — which just makes him seem like a flippant asshole.</p>



<p>But let’s look at the facts: every facet of his life has pointed him toward a career of painting professionally, and then all at once, his key to that industry is taken away — what if he didn’t&nbsp;<em>have</em>&nbsp;to do that thing every adult in your life told him he had to? Yusuke could have been rendered by this terrifying possibility, the main question of his arc being, if he paints, will it be by rote, or because he chose to recommit himself?</p>



<p>In the script as is, Yusuke has a LOT of insight and confidence for someone whose narrow worldview was just shot to hell. Shouldn’t the artist be dealing the most seriously with their own subjectivity? I think this same question could have made him more reflective on his role within the Phantom Thieves when the shit hit the fan. Would he have the conviction to know when they were going to far? Yusuke should have had a fateful moment when everything looks bad where he says, “I just don’t know.”</p>



<p>A character with conviction is one thing. If a character knows exactly how to answer a hard question, consider if that character is actually just the writer in disguise.</p>



<p><strong>Haru should have been the weird one.</strong>&nbsp;Haru’s archetype is “rich girl”. But how would you know that without being told? What about her background informs her personality? How can someone with such a huge asshole for a dad be so&nbsp;<em>nice</em>? At most, Haru should be&nbsp;<em>well-mannered</em>, but she shouldn’t actually be very good at understanding other people, because she’s never really needed anything from anyone else. Through the cracks in her manners, she should come across as tactless and unrelatable. The others should vacillate between being charmed by her, annoyed by her, and feeling pity for her. This difficulty in getting close to people should facilitate her one genuine love: gardening.</p>



<p><strong>I can’t believe I have to explain this, but Akechi shouldn’t have been a super evil sneering villain, but rather, like you, someone striving to make the world better in way that doesn’t look good from the outside.&nbsp;</strong>Akechi is implementing a plan that has been years in the making. Despite the fatalities, getting a visionary like Shido into a leadership position must be the best, most realistic chance to improve Japan. To paraphrase the bad guy from Metal Gear Rising Revengeance, Shido should seek to use corrupt shenanigans in the government to END corrupt shenanigans in the government.</p>



<p>Hey… Speaking of&nbsp;<a href="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/X04EM7vBlnE/maxresdefault.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shido</a>&nbsp;and that&nbsp;<a href="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/ZbD9INBbPM8/maxresdefault.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">other guy</a>… What a lame, un-Persona-like design.</p>



<p><strong>Makoto’s strategic mind should be pushed to its limit.</strong>&nbsp;Knowing the overwhelming odds they’re up against, and knowing how huge and complicated society is, she should have objectively appraised Akechi and Shido’s plan to reform society through political machinations as being, actually, the best way to bring about change. (This necessitates that the villains have a plan that makes sense) Ryuji and the most outspoken Phantom Thieves would push back angrily, but Makoto would remind them that their mission is to make the world better, and that maybe the mental breakdown plan is the shortest route to that. Makoto would only relent after making it clear to the Thieves that their path going forward may result in failure.</p>



<p>Makoto would still put all of her effort into planning Shido’s heist, considering every edge case, making sure everything will go smoothly, taking into account everything they’ve learned up until then. When Shido shuts down his palace manually, and Ryuji dies, everyone cries, sure, but Makoto, like… hides, not even available for Confidant excursions. She doesn’t respond to request for a Phantom Thieves meeting. She has to be tracked down and convinced that she’s not the reason Ryuji died.</p>



<p><strong>The main characters should have had to make a real sacrifice.</strong>&nbsp;The Phantom Thieves never really earned their rosy ending. These are people who chose to wrangle otherworldly powers with the specific goal of changing how the world worked. The player should have been confronted directly with the question of whether or not their choices were rooted in charity or hubris. Instead, the player gets away scot-free, with all of their friends, no mark on their record. What the hell is the moral of the story?</p>



<p><strong>Bad things need to happen to good people.&nbsp;</strong>Several times the game does somethings dramatic and then immediately reverses it. Morgana leaves the team, but not for long enough to impact any in-game choices. Ryuji vanishes, and then comes back&nbsp;<em>in the next fucking scene.&nbsp;</em>When people in Shibuya Square start panicking and disappearing toward the end, I thought that I was making irreversible changes in the real world, destroying shadows and killing civilians in the process… But, instead, my actions HAD no lasting effect on the world.</p>



<p>Drama lives in conflict. Conflict is not when the good guys beat up the bad guys. Conflict is when the good guys think the bad guys might have a point. Conflict is when the good guys are tempted to fight each other. Conflict is finding out the premise for your mission might be flawed. As is, Persona 5 is a game dripping with style but devoid of drama.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="650" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/1_J268FGhkrU5J9L5RC1KYTg.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-171" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/1_J268FGhkrU5J9L5RC1KYTg.jpeg 650w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/06/1_J268FGhkrU5J9L5RC1KYTg-300x185.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>I think the Final Fantasy XV Platinum Demo sucked, and the users at Giant Bomb agree.</title>
		<link>/2016/04/03/i-think-the-final-fantasy-xv-platinum-demo-sucked-and-the-users-at-giant-bomb-agree/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[terrytorres]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false"></guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From the thread Platinum Demo Impressions: Thank god for this thread. Looking at positive reactions on YouTube, I felt like I was living in a cuckoo clock. I downloaded the demo after watching the awesome trailer, and I played it in the same room as my wife, trying to come up with nice things to&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="2016/04/03/i-think-the-final-fantasy-xv-platinum-demo-sucked-and-the-users-at-giant-bomb-agree/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">I think the Final Fantasy XV Platinum Demo sucked, and the users at Giant Bomb agree.</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i></i><i><br />
</i><i>From the thread <a href="http://www.giantbomb.com/final-fantasy-xv/3030-21006/forums/platinum-demo-impressions-1794532/?page=1">Platinum Demo Impressions</a>:</i><br />
<i><br />
</i>Thank god for this thread. Looking at positive reactions on YouTube, I felt like I was living in a cuckoo clock. I downloaded the demo after watching the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IiI7SMQA59Q">awesome trailer</a>, and I played it in the same room as my wife, trying to come up with nice things to say while I was going through it.</p>
<p>&#8220;Okay, the controls are kinda responsive. The battle transitions are pretty smooth.&#8221; Knowing me, she said, &#8220;Do you believe anything that you&#8217;re saying?&#8221; and I finally admitted, &#8220;No.&#8221;</p>
<p>The trailer had panache and drama, and the demo didn&#8217;t have any. The coolest part was when I stepped on a switch and Leviathan soared over me and into a lake, and then just&#8230; disappeared. It&#8217;s like none of the teams working on this were ever in the same room. &#8220;Here is an ENVIRONMENT; insert SPECIAL EFFECTS; insert MONSTERS &#8211; good job, everyone.&#8221; It didn&#8217;t feel crafted at all. Really, why did any particular encounter have to occur in any particular space? It was all just Some Stuff Happening.</p>
<p>I was looking forward to the novel concept of playing in Noctis&#8217; dream to, like, get into his headspace, find out more about his character. But then I realized they set it inside of a dream for one reason: so they wouldn&#8217;t have to think about how to transition from one environment to the other. &#8220;Oh, shoot, how do we get from the forest to the toy room? Ehh, just say it was all a dream and call it a day.&#8221;</p>
<p>Remember waiting for the release of previous Final Fantasy games? The question I always remembered asking about any new one coming out was: &#8220;So what&#8217;s the new core mechanic? What&#8217;s materia all about? How does junctioning work? Sphere Grid? Gambits?&#8221; What are the new possibilities being demonstrated here? What makes this the Next Step in the series? Really, what is the POINT of this demo? What&#8217;s the Thing we were supposed to see that was meant to confirm how we shouldn&#8217;t skip this game when it comes out?</p>
<p>The demo didn&#8217;t seem to know. Instead of introducing me to a world, showing me how I should play the game, showing me what makes a strategy more worthy in one situation than another, what&#8217;s the tactical difference between dodging and warping, they were like&#8230; &#8220;Circle attacks, Square dodges. Here&#8217;s some <span style="text-decoration: line-through;">Heartless</span> Nightmares. You&#8217;re a truck now. It&#8217;s a dream. Whatever. Here&#8217;s a summon monster.&#8221;</p>
<p>Cool. Can I summon it?</p>
<p>&#8220;Uh&#8230; No.&#8221; The game barely cared that I was playing it.</p>
<p>And for those defending it as &#8220;just&#8221; a tech demo:</p>
<p><b>1)</b> I didn&#8217;t play Episode Duscae. I borrowed FF Type 0 from a friend, but found out that he had already &#8220;claimed&#8221; the digital copy of the demo, so I couldn&#8217;t play it. As a result, this demo is ALL I HAVE to go on. I also didn&#8217;t like Type 0 much, either. So I&#8217;m not gonna pay money for a game I know I don&#8217;t like to play a demo that I am now PRETTY SURE I won&#8217;t like.</p>
<p><b>2)</b> It&#8217;s not called the tech demo &#8211; it&#8217;s called the <i><b>PLATINUM</b> DEMO</i>. And then at the end of it they asked me if I wanted to pre-order the full game. If this demo isn&#8217;t supposed to be representative of the game, someone tell Square Enix, &#8217;cause they don&#8217;t seem to know.</p>
<p>At first I thought the multimedia / Florence and the Machine / Lena Hedey movie stuff was kind of cool, but it was only cool so long as I thought FFXV would be any good. Now that I don&#8217;t think it is, I realize now how stupid all of the other stuff is – they&#8217;re doing the same crap they did with FFVII and FFXIII, banking on the success of a franchise without having even finished it. In marketing this way, it&#8217;s like they&#8217;re saying, &#8220;Oh, FFXV isn&#8217;t just a GAME – it&#8217;s an EXPERIENCE!&#8221; It lowers the stakes for all of the projects under the umbrella as a result.</p>
<p>No. Stop it. Just make a game.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s also just the fact that they&#8217;re acting like this is an action RPG&#8230; While this demo has no RPG-ing, and barely any action. I never had to be thoughtful about my resources or my equipment, and the fights are impactless. The warp sword is ALMOST cool, but hitting things just doesn&#8217;t feel fun. The Nightmares just kind of melt under your flailing, and the Iron Giant is a wall you can&#8217;t be killed by.</p>
<p>If you really wanna understand how I feel, check out this video:</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/y2vCko6V4pQ" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><br />
You can watch the whole thing, or jump to 4:57.</p>
<p>Have you gotten to the part with the red circles?</p>
<p>FFXV feels like the circle on the top.<br />
<i><br />
</i><i><br />
</i><i>Other users&#8217; insights:</i></p>
<p>+ I&#8217;d gotten fairly excited for this game (never played the first demo), but this thing just knocked the wind right out of my sails. Also has me really worried about FFVII Remake, which I was already way more excited for than XV.</p>
<div>+ When you push L1 and R1 at the same it brings up a bunch of swords around Noctis, which does&#8230; something. I dunno.</div>
<div>+ Transforming to a beast showed how static the maps are. You&#8217;re telling me that this animal that includes rocks crumbling in his attack animation can&#8217;t bring a lawnchair to fall?</div>
<div>+ Also I forgot how much I hate the Japanese take on children, particularly the sounds they make when lost and befuddled. So many stupid, unnecessary &#8220;gahs&#8221; and &#8220;huhs?&#8221;</p>
</div>
<div>+ I kind of hated this(?).</p>
</div>
<div>+ I haven&#8217;t liked the design and art choices in a Final Fantasy game since IX, not a huge fan of SquareEnix&#8217;s sci-fi takes. I don&#8217;t know the man&#8217;s name but isn&#8217;t that crazy zipper guy in charge of this game and KH3? I don&#8217;t like his style.</p>
</div>
<div>+ &#8230;All that said, if I had to boil time my problem with this demo into a sentence, it would be &#8220;<b>I don&#8217;t see the product of 10 years worth of work.</b>&#8220;</div>
<div></div>
<div>+ XII I played multiple times and enjoyed thouroughly. XIII was okay at first but I got tired of it after awhile. This I just wanted nothing to do with immediately.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>So I played Suikoden (or, Sometimes old ways are best)</title>
		<link>/2015/02/04/so-i-played-suikoden-or-sometimes-old-ways-are-best/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[terrytorres]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2015 21:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false"></guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Konami&#8217;s Suikoden lacks the panache of some of its contemporaries from Square. Some of that has to do with technical know how, but also knowing how to deal with technical limits. Characters in Chrono Trigger, like most Squaresoft games of the time, have a repertoire of expressions and motions that are reused and recontextualized throughout&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="2015/02/04/so-i-played-suikoden-or-sometimes-old-ways-are-best/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">So I played Suikoden (or, Sometimes old ways are best)</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Konami&#8217;s <b>Suikoden</b> lacks the panache of some of its contemporaries from Square. Some of that has to do with technical know how, but also knowing how to deal with technical limits.</p>
<div style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="wp-content/uploads/2015/02/jRcKfGd.gif" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" border="0" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/jRcKfGd.gif" height="538" width="640" /></a></div>
<p>Characters in <b>Chrono Trigger</b>, like most Squaresoft games of the time, have a repertoire of expressions and motions that are reused and recontextualized throughout the game. Crono dealing the final blow to the Dragon Tank is incredibly awe-inspiring at the time it occurs, because we haven&#8217;t seen him pull off anything quite like that yet. The violent thrust, especially coming after being wronged by the kingdom, adds a wrathfulness to him that we may not have expected. It is empowering, then, when you can voluntarily make Crono take similar actions as you learn his more complex techniques. By the end of the game, you&#8217;ll have seen the animations quite a few times.</p>
<div style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="wp-content/uploads/2015/02/CJbsUPX.gif" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" border="0" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/CJbsUPX.gif" height="360" width="640" /></a></div>
<p>Here we have a really lovely and nuanced set of animations as the hunky doofus Flik plays host to the cougar counterfeiter Kimberly in order to enlist her. The scene has still more animations with fine detail, like hand movements and head tilts. Moments that are played like this in <b>Suikoden</b>&nbsp; &#8211; featuring a choreographed blocking particular to a location and a set of available props &#8211; can be counted on one hand. Flik and Kimberly do not drink sake again &#8211; these animations are unique to this scene. The commitment to this brief scene is admirable, but is it efficient from a development perspective &#8211; creating an asset that can&#8217;t be reused?</p>
<p>In the time before 3D models were commonplace, animations could not be shared amongst characters like they are today. Sprites aren&#8217;t like models that way. In 1995, to design and animate 108 characters for a new piece of hardware is no mean feat. A character needs to face and walk in all the cardinal directions, attack, use an item, get hurt, and be knocked out. Multiply that by about 80, and that&#8217;s lot of work for a developer diving head first into a new franchise in a relatively strange genre.</p>
<p>The choice, then, to decide where to spend time applying unique, narrative-driven animations must have been difficult. (Especially when, it seems, battle animations and field animations are run on different engines and aren&#8217;t interchangeable) Since it would be impossible to give every potential character in your party an animation appropriate to a particular point in the story, the choice was to leave leave most character reactions abstracted and up to the imagination. In exchange, story scenes with predetermined casts like the above have moments that make them stand out. That said, this particular scene is not particularly moving or informative, so in the end, the animations themselves are what make them worthwhile.</p>
<p>A lot of <b>Suikoden</b>&#8216;s charm comes from this unpredictability in the narrative and the turns in tone it takes. Each leg of the journey reveals a different weapon or ally you attempt to bring into your army, but they aren&#8217;t all alike in execution. It&#8217;s not always easy to tell ahead of time what moment will result in a new unit, or a large scale battle, or a boss fight, or a duel. Or whether all of the above might occur back to back or simultaneously, for either a short duration or a long. This pattern keeps you guessing what will come next, forcing you to always be prepared and make use of each of the assets at your disposal as often as possible.</p>
<p>Although the brisk pacing makes you eager to find what big fight is around the next corner, the most disappointing thing about Suikoden is that, for the most part, there isn&#8217;t one. Many times you may load out your party with the best equipment possible, find a great combination of characters with all the right runes and Unite attacks to make short work of any boss you&#8217;d find, and it rarely ever comes. There are only about 12 boss fights that involve the party you choose to bring with you, and half of them are weird monster lacking any narrative justification. The only way to measure the success of your tactics otherwise is against the randomly encountered riffraff along the way. It&#8217;s a shame when there are so many interesting ways that 30 runes and 80 playable characters combine that there aren&#8217;t that many appropriate challenges to test them on.</p>
<p>The other great challenges you face come in the form of great battles between thousands of tiny soldiers or one-on-one duels. They&#8217;re both essentially games of rock-paper-scissors. That makes them sound simplistic &#8211; and really, they are &#8211; but that&#8217;s not the whole story. Large-scale battles let you make your rock, paper, or scissors really big if you have the right people on your side, and duels challenge you to decipher which instrument your opponent will use based on context clues. The fact that so much rests on each decision, and that these situations come up as rarely as they do, makes the moments up to your choice quite intense.</p>
<p>What really makes <b>Suikoden</b>&nbsp;work, the urge that drives you even when you can&#8217;t quite tell what character you should be using or how difficult the coming dungeon will be, is the constant growth you enjoy as times goes on, like a lovely colorful garden. Even just the recruits you gather mandatorily add up to make a huge cast. That so many people are willing to join you, and that so many of them have sound reasons for doing so &#8211; the main ones being vengeance and employment, but there&#8217;s also glory and a hope to belong to something larger &#8211; reinforces the worth of your objective. Their personalities are portrayed succinctly and surprisingly deftly through a character portrait, their combat ability, and a few lines. Letting imagination take care of the rest, the 108-member cast of <b>Suikoden</b>&nbsp;is less annoying&nbsp;and/or pointless than most of the 40 playable characters in&nbsp;<b>Chrono Cross</b>.</p>
<p>Games like&nbsp;<b>Suikoden</b>&nbsp;invite player imagination by applying just enough abstraction in the right places. Older games than this have suggested fantastic battles between opposing armies, but few have let you put a face and a name to so many individual participants before. There is a limit, of course. You can&#8217;t identify each of the thousands of soldiers that fight for the Liberation Army in the grand battles that occur a few times through the game, but knowing all the kinds of people that you&#8217;ve met across the land, you can assume what they might be like.</p>
<p>Liberation Army headquarters in the castle on the lake is a precursor to the hub worlds of later years, the lobbies of MMORPGs, the Normandy of <b>Mass Effect</b>&nbsp;&#8211; a small space that indicates the largeness of the world outside it with each addition to your war assets. With so many of your supplies being provided within your own domain, Suikoden could have done what later games would do, and simply teleport you to your next mission when necessary. Instead, they kept the iconic 16-bit world map with which you can go from place to place, random encounters suggesting the severity of each journey. Crossing the land by foot does provide a sense of ownership and responsibility that helps make your fight for peace worthwhile.</p>
<p>Some aspects of old design should be thrown out, and some aspects are simply tied to the technology or the trends of the time and die off naturally. The <i>world map</i> is a unique vestige of old design. It was not abandoned because it was a feature that arose from having to deal with old technology, but because even new technology is incapable of presenting an entire world in realistic proportions, and new trends wouldn&#8217;t allow for a diminutive version of your protagonist crossing even tinier mountains to get from place to place. Today&#8217;s method of representation, after the graphical arms race of the past decade and a half, has come to lean on 1:1 realism. The virtual space within games today are bigger than ever &#8211; there is more traversable surface area, anyway &#8211; but it can be argued in some ways that, without being able to artfully present an entire explorable globe, the scope is smaller.</p>
<p>At around the same time,&nbsp;<b>Final Fantasy X</b>, <b>Breath of Fire: Dragon Quarter</b>, even <b>Wild Arms 4</b>&nbsp;were all games that did not let the player traverse a world map, even while previous entries in their series did. (<b>Dragon Quest 8</b>, interestingly, would pull an Elder Scrolls and make the distance between towns and dungeons realistic in scale &#8211; while keeping random battles). A game could not be on a powerhouse console and fail to deliver on visuals, nor could a game deliver on visuals and find a way to justify the minimalist abstraction of an old-style world map. I tend to believe that the questing beast of realistic scale lead to the downfall of JRPGs that struck a few years back, leading to games that could not rewrite the traditional JRPG script to match these narrower scopes. <i>(Consider <b>Kingdom Hearts</b>, a game about traveling multiple worlds that are each made up of about a dozen rooms or so, or <b>Xenosaga</b>, a game about humanity and the cosmos that is completely linear &#8211; but, mostly, consider the shittier games that copied both of these)</i></p>
<p>Naturally, it took years of failure to adapt to new trends for players and developers alike to realize that there is a place for old design. That&#8217;s why <b>Bravely Default</b>, a 2014 handheld game with a world map, received such good response in comparison to <b>Lightning Returns</b>.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s also why &#8211; I hope &#8211; Sony and Konami had the good sense to bring back interesting gems like <b>Suikoden</b>&nbsp;for reappraisal. Looking back, simplicity and abstraction in a game may seem like symptoms of technological constraint, but when you consider the best possible choices that could be made at the time, the effectiveness of some ideas never truly age.</p>
<p>The question at the end of the day is, how do you best provide any kind of fulfilling experience? By knowing when to show off and knowing when to let the user&#8217;s imagination do the rest of the work.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>So I started playing Grand Theft Auto 5</title>
		<link>/2014/01/15/so-i-started-playing-grand-theft-auto-5/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terry]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 16:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false"></guid>

					<description><![CDATA[At first I was excited. Now I&#8217;m ready to stop. I wanted to start a mission with the awful paparazzi guy, so I stole a car to get to that side of town. About 15 seconds later, the police are on me, and my wanted level is at 3 &#8211; y&#8217;know, three white stars up&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="2014/01/15/so-i-started-playing-grand-theft-auto-5/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">So I started playing Grand Theft Auto 5</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At first I was excited. Now I&#8217;m ready to stop.</p>
<p>I wanted to start a mission with the awful paparazzi guy, so I stole a car to get to that side of town. About 15 seconds later, the police are on me, and my wanted level is at 3 &#8211; y&#8217;know, three white stars up in the corner. I thought maybe I could start the mission and the police would go away. No, I can&#8217;t do missions while the police are chasing me. So I drive around for a few minutes, into a dead end, jump out of my car, over a divider, and just sprint away.</p>
<p>When I finally lose them, I steal another car, evade police detection, and make it to the side of town with the paparazzo. But as I turn into the driveway to start the mission, thinking that the mission would start automatically when I did so (which usually happens), I end up bumping into the paparazzo, who just kind of&#8230; runs away.</p>
<p>So I drive waaay up the street and wait for his little map indicator to come back, drive back, park away from him, get out, and start the mission.</p>
<p>Then as we walk down the street he gets hit by a bus making a U-turn. Mission Failed.</p>
<p>I always thought the growing realism of sandbox games only made them less fun. Things like having to elude the police in a stolen car should be fun, unless it&#8217;s getting in the way of something else I want to do.</p>
<p>Another big problem I&#8217;m having is that I&#8217;m sick of GTA protagonists somehow being &#8220;better&#8221; than the people they&#8217;re working for. Every word out of Franklin&#8217;s mouth is always about how dumb or petty other characters are, or how stupid the thing he&#8217;s being asked to do is.</p>
<p>What sucks about that is I <i>also</i> happen to think that all the characters are stupid and petty, and everything we do is stupid. I did three really dull missions in a row, and for each one Franklin mostly just complained through the whole thing.</p>
<p><a href="2013/04/03/so-i-played-bayonetta-again/">For the most part</a>, the player and the protagonist should want the same thing, and for the most part, that thing should be accomplishing the next mission objective. Contrast the self-aware reluctance of Franklin with the doggedly sadistic passions of the Third Street Saints in any given Saints Row. When the missions objective reads, &#8220;Save Shaundi,&#8221; and <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=85xMRa5UqgQ">I Need a Hero</a> is playing, you better believe the Boss is saying to his pals, &#8220;I&#8217;m gonna fucking save Shaundi!&#8221; When Bayonetta slinks into a room and says, &#8220;I&#8217;m here to beat up Angels,&#8221; and then Angels start coming after her, you&#8217;re gonna say, &#8220;<i>I am also here to beat up angels.</i>&#8221; The least you should do for the player is reinforce that what they&#8217;re being asked to do is worth doing, that they and the game are on the same page.</p>
<p>So the 15th time Franklin asked something to the effect of, &#8220;Why am I even doing this?&#8221; I was like, &#8220;Good question!&#8221; and quit the game.</p>
<p>I actually really like Franklin as a character. His reluctance to do dirty work despite his obvious skill at it says a lot about the unrelenting siren call of criminal life. That same struggle was easily the best part of Niko&#8217;s story in Grand Theft Auto 4, as well. But that motif is somewhat self-sabotaging in a game that doesn&#8217;t feel the need to invite deep thought about any of its other messages. The talk-news and the commercial segments that parodize vapid American pop culture seem less biting now than they did in 2008. Four whole seasons of South Park have come out since then.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s also a seeming confusion between what counts as satire and what is just biased observation. Yeah, west coast tennis instructors <i>do</i> have affairs with clients. Sure, aging black women <i>do</i> uses cliched mantras to inspire self-confidence. Uh-huh, pop sensations <i>are</i> actually older than they let on. And? The observations themselves fall flat since the characters themselves aren&#8217;t deep enough to invite scrutiny over their ways of life, nor are they broad enough as caricatures to invite laughter and derision. Cut scenes start up and I just twiddle my thumbs until Rockstar is done thinking they&#8217;ve made a point about some facet of modern life, waiting until I can pick the controller up again and play the goddamn game.</p>
<p>The parts of the story I&#8217;ve liked best so far are scenes with Franklin and his allies in crime, mostly because they&#8217;re actually focused on character growth. At this point there&#8217;s still a question of how far Franklin is willing to go to gain independence, and his respect for others shifts as he tries to answer that question for himself. What&#8217;s nice about this pre-Michael segment of the game is that there&#8217;s far less &#8220;parody&#8221; &#8211; more plot development and less lame &#8220;satire&#8221;.</p>
<p>The reasons there isn&#8217;t as much &#8220;biting satire&#8221; in this early segment of the game is that there is nothing to satirize. People like Franklin &#8211; stuck in a cycle of violence with friends and opportunities constantly drifting in and out of his life at with the whims of society at large &#8211; actually exist in the real world. If there are any jokes to be made here, they&#8217;re only to be touched by writers who know what the hell they&#8217;re doing. Even Rockstar&#8217;s writers know well enough.</p>
<p>So they stick with the same old targets: rich white people, Fox News, and most kinds of women. &#8220;Okay, writing staff, here are your Safe Topics. These things are funny. Everything else is <i>off limits</i>. We don&#8217;t want to confuse or alienate anyone who matters!&#8221;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://www.gta5tv.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/gta-5-artwork-51827938befaa.jpg" width="600" /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>So I watched Beyond: Two Souls</title>
		<link>/2014/01/02/so-i-watched-beyond-two-souls/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terry]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2014 22:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false"></guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I say &#8220;watched,&#8221; you may assume, to suggest that Beyond: Two Souls is more of a movie than a game. In reality, that isn&#8217;t quite true, either. Beyond: Two Souls isn&#8217;t really a game or a movie. And I don&#8217;t say this to suggest that Beyond: Two Souls is somehow bolder or more expansive than&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="2014/01/02/so-i-watched-beyond-two-souls/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">So I watched Beyond: Two Souls</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I say &#8220;watched,&#8221; you may assume, to suggest that <b>Beyond: Two Souls</b> is more of a movie than a game. In reality, that isn&#8217;t quite true, either. <b>Beyond: Two Souls</b> isn&#8217;t really a game <i>or</i> a movie. And I don&#8217;t say this to suggest that <b>Beyond: Two Souls</b> is somehow bolder or more expansive than either a video game or a movie, or that it defies categorization. I refuse to put a label on <b>Beyond: Two Souls </b>because, if I were to do so, whatever category I were to put it into would be irrevocably worsened.</p>
<p>It is not a video game, nor is it a movie. If pressed to define it, I&#8217;d say it&#8217;s a twelve-hour piece of performance art where some innocent fuck is tricked into spending sixty dollars on a boring, useless item, then is compelled to use it despite a mounting sense of rage of disgust.</p>
<p>* * *</p>
<p>My relationship with David Cage, <b>Beyond: Two Souls</b> intrepid W R I T O R and D E R E K T O R, is a complicated one, except that it&#8217;s actually very simple, because I hate him and I think he&#8217;s a piece of crap (and a racist). I loathed <b>Indigo Prophecy </b>with the force of a thousand suns&#8211;enough to temporarily blind me to the surprising successes of the later <b>Heavy Rain</b>, which I now begrudgingly admit is an innovative and highly enjoyable piece of game-making, for all its wacky Europeanisms.</p>
<p>So I approached <b>Beyond: Two Souls</b> with a skeptical but overall neutral point-of-view. I didn&#8217;t want to deprive myself of a fun experience, but it&#8217;s hard not to feel twice-shy being once so bitten.&nbsp; And there was a very specific moment in our playthrough, towards the end of the first act, that made me go cold with incredulity, and erased any charitable feelings I&#8217;d allocated for Cage.</p>
<p>There was a point in which Jodie, our implausibly old-name-having protagonist, has to walk through a ruined  medical facility. There is an encounter with an enemy that asks you to  follow the on-screen prompts to evade danger and progress. We missed  several prompts somewhat clumsily, and I was actually rather surprised that we cleared the challenge, remembering how easy it was for Madison Page to meet any number of context-sensitive grisly deaths in her encounter with the good doctor in <b>Heavy Rain.</b></p>
<p>Anyway, immediately following this sequence, Jodie got stuck in the wall trying  to exit the room, frozen and inanimate (but still crying and panting&#8211;thanks). Ah. Well. Glitches happen, it&#8217;s no <b>Fallout: New Vegas</b>&#8211;at least not yet. So we restarted the chapter, participating in the QTE fight again, this time never missing a prompt. It was at this point that we realized is that, despite how much better we were at pressing  the appropriate buttons this time, the scene played out in exactly the  same manner as it had previously. Our suceesses and failures merited no rewards or consequences within the scene.</p>
<p>What we realized is that were never really truly <i>participating</i> at all. We were just along for the ride, humoring <b>Beyond: Two Souls</b>.</p>
<p>What greatly angered us was another realization. Does David Cage know that we&#8217;re humoring him, or does he really think <i>he&#8217;s</i> humoring <i>us?</i></p>
<p>* * *</p>
<p>There is another point in <b>B:TS</b> where Jodie has to run away from  something terrible that&#8217;s chasing her. Just to see what would happen, I  put the controller down on the floor. Would Jodie be captured by this  monster and torn limb from limb?<br /><i><br /></i> No. Some moments later, Jodie, on her own, ran away.</p>
<p>(Spoilers will get slightly more persistent from here forward, but only slightly. After all, you&#8217;ve seen everything that happens in this &#8220;game&#8221;&#8211;the reversals and surprises and betrayals and losses you encounter as Jodie are all rote recitations of the same Hollywood junk you&#8217;ve seen crammed into games for the last fifteen years. Even the least savvy of eight year-olds can tell you the most shocking twists to expect in such a formulaic offering. DUDES! Your idealized mentor father-figure is actually MORALLY AMBIGUOUS OMMMMMGGGGAAAAAAADD!?!?!?!?!?!)</p>
<p>* * *</p>
<p>Later, we wanted to  find out if it was actually possible to get intimate with one of the  other characters in the game during a romantically-charged scene. (And I don&#8217;t mean &#8220;emotionally close,&#8221; I mean &#8220;can we get THIS penis in THAT vagina?&#8221;) So I Googled &#8220;beyond two souls walkthrough&#8221;. What a redundant phrase.  For the most part, <b>Beyond: Two Souls</b> is a walkthrough of itself.</p>
<p>We discovered that there was, indeed, a way that the chapter could end  with sex AND a Playstation Network Trophy. We figured we&#8217;d go for it. As  long as we&#8217;re going through this, we might as well get some gamer cred,  or whatever.</p>
<p>However, there was a disclaimer in the walkthrough for this particular portion of the game:</p>
<blockquote><p>NOTE! If in [the chapter] &#8220;Like Other Girls&#8221;, the protagonist was groped  by the bar’s clientele, no closer relationship with Ryan will happen.</p></blockquote>
<p>I know you&#8217;re probably reading this sentence because you had already  finished the previous sentence, but I want you to go back and read it  again.</p>
<p>In this story about the supposed complexity of a human being&#8217;s life and  identity over the course of many years, it is suggested that <i>because Jodie was sexually abused several years prior, she is incapable of intimacy in the present.</i></p>
<p>There aren&#8217;t many choices you can make in a chapter that actually  affects the events of another chapter &#8211; just one reason the boneheaded  achronological narrative is just a bloody smoking hole in the foot of  the story &#8211; but Cage made sure to fit in the little moral that <i>if you didn&#8217;t have the foresight not to avoid your attempted rape, you are damaged goods.</i></p>
<p>Not only is this thing void of good ideas, whatever ideas it manages to  portray are toxic for society and antagonistic to humanity. </p>
<p>* * *</p>
<p>While experiencing <b>B:TS</b> I was often on Twitter, writing thoughts about  it as they occurred to me. Although this form of expression is troubling  in several ways, it is appropriate for the works of David Cage. Deep  analysis isn&#8217;t terribly necessary. All that needs to be done is present  without irony exactly what occurs in <b>Beyond: Two Souls</b>, and any  intelligent person can construe that it is lesser than garbage.</p>
<p>What follows are more detailed extrapolations of my Tweets as I  experienced <b>B:TS</b>. These are essentially a list of observations in the  order they were made.</p>
<ul></p>
<li><b>B:TS</b> opens with Ellen Page&#8217;s talking head, sounding confused.  This is running motif in Cage&#8217;s work &#8211; big heads seeming unhappy.  Supposedly, this is the end of the events of the story, and the  following chapters take place BEFORE this point. This  scene is mostly meaningless considering we have no idea who this is  or when this takes place. It&#8217;s not like Sunset  Boulevard &#8211; there are no expectations set up here.</li>
<p></p>
<li>After every chapter, the wavy-looking &#8220;timeline&#8221; for Jodie&#8217;s  life is displayed, along with the name of the next Chapter and at what  point on the timeline it occurs. It would be neat if this were a screen  in which you could select what chapter you wanted to experience next. It  would even feel somewhat immersive if the next chapter did not proceed  until you pressed X to indicate you were ready to relive this memory.  Instead, the timeline is just a loading screen, loading whatever part of  Jodie&#8217;s life Cage thinks you should walk through next. Though it is  marginally useful in finding out at what point the next chapter occurs  based on chapter you&#8217;ve already seen.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Child Jodie is a pretty good actor. Way better than the French kids Cage got to play children from Philadelphia in <b>Heavy Rain</b>.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Willem Dafoe plays Jodie&#8217;s mentor and father figure, Nathan,  trying to find out how she connects to her invisible psychic/ghost  friend, Aiden. He does it through all the usual bullshit ways movie  paranormalologists detects psychics &#8211; by asking her to pick cards with  pictures on them.</li>
<p></p>
<li>You can control Aiden by interacting with objects marked by blue  dots and knocking them over. This is Aiden&#8217;s primary purpose: knocking  shit over. The game asks you to knock things over. But then at some  point you knock something over and everyone in the lab starts freaking  out. We start to think, &#8220;Okay, I guess we&#8217;ll stop knocking shit over.&#8221;  But the story doesn&#8217;t proceed if you don&#8217;t knock more shit over. In order  to convey that Aiden is sometimes &#8220;out of control&#8221; and &#8220;dangerous&#8221; the  story forces us to force Aiden to knock shit over. Aiden doesn&#8217;t feel  &#8220;out of control&#8221; to me. He just seems to be stuck in a story in which he  is &#8220;out of control,&#8221; despite the fact he is completely in my control.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Nathan, calming Jodie down, says, &#8220;It&#8217;s alright, Jodie, it&#8217;s  over.&#8221; Jodie responds, &#8220;It will never be over.&#8221; ಠ_ಠ Yep, because real  people talk this way.</li>
<p></p>
<li>The next chapter, bafflingly, takes place at Sheikh Ahmed&#8217;s  black tie gala. At this point, Jodie is in the CIA, and she&#8217;s going to  use Aiden to find out what important secrets she can find in Sheikh  Ahmed&#8217;s house. It&#8217;s one of the few times you have reign to float around  and do stuff. Unlike other games in which you can decide how to use your  powers to solve the problem in front of you, Aiden can only use certain  powers on certain objects that the story needs to be interacted with to  progress. Imagine a Legend of Zelda game in which the room you are in  has a locked door, and there are switches all over the walls, and there  is only one switch that opens it, but that switch is glowing blue, and  the other switches actually don&#8217;t do anything. That is every sequence  with Aiden.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Jodie is wearing a dress with her entire back exposed. The  texture of her back is somewhat terrifying &#8211; as though her skin is paper  thin and you an see every muscle fiber under it. This is one of the  most unsettling dips into the Uncanny Valley, but sure not the last.</li>
<p></p>
<li>The bathroom signs for Ahmed&#8217;s place feature a <i>veiled</i> face over the door for the women&#8217;s bathroom, and a <i>bearded</i> face over the door for the men&#8217;s bathroom. This seems racist to me, but then I&#8217;ve never been to the Middle East.</li>
<p></p>
<li>The next chapter involves a birthday party at some brat&#8217;s house.  Nathan thinks it&#8217;ll be good to meet kids my age. He already picked out  the present for the birthday girl: an old collection of the works of  Edgar Allen Poe. Our guess is that the girl will think it&#8217;s a terrible  gift and that it will act as an additional reason we should feel  absolved for torturing her later. We are right.</li>
<p></p>
<li>The party has beer and weed. We indulge in both. We also get to  pick the music. We picked disco. Another brat said it was a stupid, and  changed the song. We weren&#8217;t sure if that moment was to get us to hate that  girl, or just <b>B:TS</b> trying to simply negate another one of my choices.</li>
<p></p>
<li>You can score with some limey kid, but in the end, he and the  others turn on you for being a &#8220;witch.&#8221; Their bright idea for dealing with  witches? Lock them in a closet. <i>&#8216;Cause that won&#8217;t backfire.</i></li>
<p></p>
<li>It totally backfires. This is the only point in the story where  we feel as though Jodie, Aiden, and us are on the same side. We toss  knives and set fires. We&#8217;re finally having fun, despite how blurry and  floaty Aiden is.</li>
<p></p>
<li>There is a chapter that has us training to be in a special  division of the CIA. It plays out like an actual montage. Pressing X to  run over tires. Pressing X to solve&#8230; math equations? Flicking the  analog stick to punch dudes. Do we really need this shit? I have an  invisible ghost friend.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Suddenly Aiden can &#8220;heal&#8221; wounds by just kind of floating over them. This is used again I think four more times afterward. </li>
<p></p>
<li>Jodie&#8217;s step parents are really funny. The mother might actually  be a good actor, but it&#8217;s hard to tell in this game, since nobody says  things that regular people say. The father is hilarious. He just is  always angry and often shouting. At some point I think you get a Trophy  based on whether or not you display hatred toward him.</li>
<p></p>
<li>For the most part, the only way for things to progress is for  Aiden to knock hist over. This could easily be called Knock Shit Over  Simulator Pro.</li>
<p></p>
<li>The first wham-bam &#8220;blockbuster&#8221; sequence involves going through  a ruined medical facility where people are trying to harness the  awesome power of ghosts for ??????? reasons. It is at this point that  all the seams show, if they haven&#8217;t already.</li>
<ul></p>
<li>All QTEs are rigged in your favor.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Solving puzzles means switching to Aiden to knock over the &#8220;correct&#8221; thing &#8211; Aiden, really, is just a more complicated QTE.</li>
<p></p>
<li>You can read memories from dead people&#8217;s corpses or possessions, but they only tell you what you already know.</li>
<p></p>
<li>People respond to crises and tragedy in ways that don&#8217;t make sense. &#8220;Go!&#8230; Nothing but&#8230; DEATH&#8230; in there!&#8221; </li>
<p></p>
<li>The logic of Aiden&#8217;s powers and the ghost world are completely  inconsistent. Sometimes Aiden can help Jodie, and sometimes she&#8217;s all on  her own. Aiden can beat up ghosts, but they can&#8217;t do anything to him.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Jodie does things she should know better than doing. Like taking the elevator instead of the stairs in an emergency. What the FUCK is actually wrong with you. I don&#8217;t care if you have a magic zombie-goast pal to bail you out&#8211;take the stairs, you lazy bum.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Jodie seems to know how to find and shut down the power for a  unique piece of machinery. She doesn&#8217;t think to just cut all of the  wires around her, but instead has to cross through a ghost tornado for  reasons.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Fighting the ghosts &#8211; which should be a big deal, they&#8217;re  fucking flying screaming horrors that have the power to make people kill  themselves and each other &#8211; is exactly as fun as knocking shit over in  the rest of <b>B:TS</b>, in that it&#8217;s not. They could have invented a different  action specifically for fighting the ghosts, but it&#8217;s the some input as  knocking over paper and water bottles and crap.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Nothing is scary or surprising, because most humans have seen a  movie before, and sound cues indicate what&#8217;s going to happen all of the  time.</li>
<p></p>
<li>The engine Cage uses to make these games only heightens the  excitement and drama of small things &#8211; most famously The Lizard trial in  <b>Heavy Rain</b>. It is incapable of capturing the complexity of a fantastic  action sequences the same way most video games already can pretty well.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Jodie&#8217;s thighs are <i>too fucking thin.</i></li>
</ul>
<p></p>
<li>Jodie tells Nathan, &#8220;Don&#8217;t let them do that again. If  they open a passage, there&#8217;ll be nothing left.&#8221; The bad news? I think we&#8217;re supposed to be surprised that they do it again. The worse news? Because of the way the  story works, it won&#8217;t be relevant for another 10 hours.</li>
<p></p>
<li>The chapter in which Jodie is homeless and makes friends with  homeless people invites a question for anyone interested in seeing more  scenarios that aren&#8217;t typically presented in video games: Why isn&#8217;t the  whole game about using your ghost powers to overcome and navigate the  challenges of being homeless? Because 1) Cage does not have anything  poignant to say about being homeless, 2) he hasn&#8217;t met enough black  people in his life to write about more than one in the same story for  too long, and 3) despite all the smoke he blows about taking video games  to a new level, he&#8217;s afraid NOT to put in more scenes that involve the  same guns and violence that every video game has.</li>
<p></p>
<li>There&#8217;s a point where you can accept someone&#8217;s sexual proposition, but even if you do Jodie just <i>changes her mind about it.</i>  Again, your choices are negated if David Cage doesn&#8217;t like them, yet  he&#8217;s still willing to put women in dangerous and titillating situations  without seriously confronting their consequences.</li>
<p></p>
<li>There are maybe one or two times where Jodie has prophetic  visions in her dreams. These were likely put in so the plot would make  slightly more sense. Since the story is presented out of order, it  totally doesn&#8217;t work.</li>
<p></p>
<li>By the way. Aiden is pronounced throughout the game as  &#8220;Eye-den,&#8221; except for one point when Willem Dafoe pronounces it  &#8220;Ay-den.&#8221; He probably pronounced it that way because that is how you are  supposed pronounce the name Aiden. Cage did not deign to correct  Willem, even if it meant an inconsistency.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Women in David Cage games exist to 1) be fucked or threatened  with unwanted fucking, 2) be beaten up, 3) be impregnated, 4) cry, or 5)  all of the above.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Flashbacks to Child Jodie are mostly complete wastes of time. The only good part is when you have a snowball fight.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Girls&#8217; Night Out is the chapter is which Jodie is whiny,  entitled, and uses her powers for stupid reasons. Rather than making you  appreciate Jodie&#8217;s growth, it only highlights how often Jodie is whiny  and entitled throughout the story.</li>
<p></p>
<li>The Navajo chapter has already been equated to a bad episode of  the X-Files. Doesn&#8217;t that sound great, though? What if every chapter was  Jodie drifting into some town and solving their ghost problems?</li>
<p></p>
<li>Believe it or not, the sequence in which a white girl teaches a  Navajo family how to deal with the vengeful spirit that their ancestors  foolishly summoned to repel the White Man 200 years ago is still not the  most racist thing David Cage has written.</li>
<p></p>
<li>The horses on the Navajo ranch are wearing English bridles,  while they should be wearing Western bridles. They&#8217;re the only horses in  the game, I mean, come on</li>
<p></p>
<li>Also, nearly every time there is an elevator in this game, a  sign nearby refers to it as a &#8220;Lift&#8221;. It&#8217;s like in <b>Heavy Rain</b> when  abandoned lots were referred to as &#8220;wastelands&#8221;. Cage would never let a  copy editor near his precious script.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Nathan&#8217;s back story is illuminated <i>very</i> quickly<i> </i>and <i>very</i> late. Cage probably had exactly 6 hours with Willem Dafoe to just cram everything in.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Also, I know I said Nathan was Jodie&#8217;s father figure, but is he <i>really?</i> Seriously.<i> </i>I can&#8217;t think of a single nice thing he does for Jodie, or even a single lasting lesson he imparts on her. Nathan&#8217;s assistant Cole is nicer to Jodie than basically anyone else in the story, and he&#8217;s still just a &#8220;supporting&#8221; member of the cast.</li>
<p></p>
<li>The one environment that gets reused over and over is the dorm  that Jodie stays in while working with Nathan. It&#8217;s suggested at one  point we should feel sentimental about it, even though it is the least  impressive looking residence in the whole game and nothing pleasant  ever happens there.</li>
<p></p>
<li>It&#8217;s during The Dinner scene where we had the brilliant  revelation that the game might have been better if the chapters were  divided between those in which you controlled Jodie and those in which you  controlled Aiden. As is, the opportunites where you can control Aiden  seem arbitrary, and when you actively control one to sabotage the other,  as in this scene, it seems as though your presence at best deteriorates  the story and its logic, and at worse puts you in control of the  character who is in the least interesting situation at the time.</li>
<p></p>
<li>David Cage loooooves making women take showers with their hands  against the wall being all live, &#8220;Uhhh, I just looove being NAKED and  wet.&#8221; It&#8217;s not sexy, though, because Jodie washes her hair while it&#8217;s  still pulled back in a ponytail. <i>Grrrrrross. </i>No shampoo, no conditioner, just a pile of wet, dirty, smelly hair trapped in a festering pile. Help <b>me</b>, Aiden!</li>
<p></p>
<li>It seems to be completely arbitrary, as well, what actions get  QTE prompts. Opening a bottle of wine gets two. Putting on a diving suit  doesn&#8217;t get any.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Ellen Page is a fine actress. But she just doesn&#8217;t have the range to hold my interest or sympathy for 20 hours.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Ellen Page is also one of the least expressive actors in Hollywood. She&#8217;s known for having a somewhat monotone voice and deadpan delivery, no matter her role. This may make her an excellent choice for some movie roles, but this makes her particularly poor one for an animated medium. Compare Ellen Page&#8217;s extremely faithful motion capture to that of Kristen Bell, from the <b>Assassin&#8217;s Creed</b> series, and you&#8217;ll see a markedly less wooden character model, despite the less sophisticated technology. Bell is a naturally more animated, physically/facially/vocally expressive actress, which makes her tremendously more interesting and engaging to look at when rendered as a 3D nonhuman.</li>
<p></p>
<li>There&#8217;s a scene in which someone gets news that someone they  cared about died. It&#8217;s hard to tell, though, because literally no one  acts like they would have had it occurred in reality. Think about it: if  someone asks you, &#8220;What&#8217;s happened?&#8221; after getting this news (first  off, fuck them for not figuring it out while they&#8217;re in the room with  you) would you say, &#8220;A truck&#8230; wrong side of the road&#8230; drunk  driver&#8230; sentence fragments&#8230; just phrases!&#8221;</li>
<p></p>
<li>The saddest part of the game is that there is a dedication to  someone who had died. Which means, even having known the death of a  friend and colleague, David Cage STILL wrote this scene. This man  doesn&#8217;t know what empathy means. He can&#8217;t even empathize that Americans  use elevators and not lifts!!</li>
<p></p>
<li>And again, it&#8217;s even more jarring when, like, <i>name actors</i> have to work with <i>horseshit</i>.</li>
<p></p>
<li>There is a chapter that is, basically, just the first act of  Metal Gear Solid 4, except with a lot more floating around and  wondering, &#8220;What the hell do I do now?&#8221; Yep &#8211; that&#8217;s David Cage! Pushing the  envelope by making you kill brown people in a blown-out desert town! In a  video game, no less!</li>
<p></p>
<li>Jodie gets betrayed at some point. The suggestion is that we, too,  should feel betrayed, but by this point she has made so many poor  decisions &#8211; decision the game railroaded you and her into making &#8211; that  it just feels like it&#8217;s her fault. In another game this would feel like a  revelation. Here, it just doesn&#8217;t fit in with the birthday party and  the homeless pregnancy and the estranged father figure and all the other  stuff that happens in the story that has nothing to do with CIA  missions.</li>
<p></p>
<li>There are no fat people in this game. Cage probably hates them, too.</li>
<p></p>
<li>In case you were wondering, yes, even while on a government mission, Jodie is still whiny and panicky and complaining. </li>
<p></p>
<li>Your purported love interest is a terrible person who lies to  you. You have the option to forgive him, when you should have the option  to push him into a fast-moving river.</li>
<p></p>
<li>As <b>B:TS</b> approaches its &#8220;climax,&#8221; several new characters are suddenly introduced who are conveniently &#8220;the bad guys&#8221;.</li>
<p></p>
<li>If you put down the controller during a bout with one of these  villains, you will still live and they will still die. They are so  inconsequential that you don&#8217;t even need to fight them to succeed.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Jodie is knocked out by antagonizing forces more than once after walking through a  door. Considering she can see through walls, this likely means that  she is <i>an idiot.</i> </li>
<p></p>
<li>The only reason that the climax occurs is because several people do really stupid things that make no sense. </li>
</ul>
<p>Every once in a while <b>B:TS</b> made us say, &#8220;If only this was the whole game.&#8221; If only the whole game was spent spying on enemies governments. If only the whole game was exorcising ghosts. If only the whole game was trying to get a boyfriend. If only the whole game was stealing and turning tricks on the street.</p>
<p>One of the hallmarks of the truly great auteur is the ability to self-edit, and show self-restraint. Tarentino edited Gogo Yubari&#8217;s vengeance-seeking twin sister Sakura out of the already incredibly genre-bending and seemingly unrestrained <b>Kill</b> <b>Bill</b>. He prioritized a cohesive, coherent narrative over simply cramming in all the stories he&#8217;d originally hoped to. And Cage seems to think of himself as an auteur, but ultimately he shows no fidelity to his own narrative&#8211;he is too eager to spill his every thought to just buckle-down, focus, and <i>tell us a goddamned good story</i>. Like a five year-old recounting his day at school, <b>Beyond: Two Souls </b>is filled with &#8220;and thens.&#8221; <i>And then she&#8217;s a witch with magic powers. And then she&#8217;s a secret agent. And then she&#8217;s an angsty teenager. And then she&#8217;s a jilted lover. And then she&#8217;s a homeless person. And then she&#8217;s a great white savior to a bunch of hunky Injuns. </i>And, like listening to a five year-old, I can only nod my head woodenly, praying his mother will save me from his incoherent babble before I eat my own hands out of boredom and frustration.</p>
<p>Instead, it&#8217;s all of these things and more. Nothing lasts long enough for it to become important. It&#8217;s none of these things and less.</p>
<p><b>tl;dr: &#8220;SHIMISANIIIIII!!!!!&#8221;</b></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>So I finally finished Soul Sacrifice (or, The Nature of Memories)</title>
		<link>/2013/09/18/so-i-finally-finished-soul-sacrifice-or-the-nature-of-memories/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terry]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2013 20:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false"></guid>

					<description><![CDATA[(I mean, it&#8217;s not really a game you complete, but I think I&#8217;d like to declare my being finished with it) So a while ago, I talked about the method that games use to explore certain ideas. The conclusion I was trying to reach is that a story&#8217;s message doesn&#8217;t have to be clumsily delivered&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="2013/09/18/so-i-finally-finished-soul-sacrifice-or-the-nature-of-memories/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">So I finally finished Soul Sacrifice (or, The Nature of Memories)</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="http://i129.photobucket.com/albums/p214/kefkajr/ss-banner_zpseda38162.jpg" /></p>
<p>(I mean, it&#8217;s not really a game you complete, but I think I&#8217;d like to declare my being finished with it)</p>
<p><a href="2013/06/19/so-i-played-remember-me-and-then-i-stopped/">So a while ago</a>, I talked about the method that games use to explore certain ideas. The conclusion I was trying to reach is that a story&#8217;s message doesn&#8217;t have to be clumsily delivered through its plot or parroted by characters when you can use things like game mechanics and world-building and repetition of ideas (in other mediums these are called <i>motifs</i>) to influence the tone of the story and the lasting impression the player takes from it.</p>
<p><b>Vagrant Story</b> is not the Holy Grail of gaming I once thought, but its script is still a benchmark for video games. The plot focuses on an infiltration mission and political machinations, but through its protagonist it explored the nature of human memory and its importance in forming one&#8217;s identity several months before the Christopher Nolan&#8217;s <b>Memento</b> would do the same thing.</p>
<p>Certainly, Vagrant Story was not the first game where the nebulous nature of a character&#8217;s memories (or lack thereof, as many will remember how common amnesia was as a trope compared to now) were integral to the understanding of the story, but after Vagrant Story, I can think of plenty of games that put the nature of their characters memories, personalities, and identities front and center &#8211; especially where Square Enix was concerned.</p>
<p>In games like <b>Final Fantasy IX</b>, there was still some subtlety to the proceedings. At the game&#8217;s outset, the mystery of Vivi&#8217;s identity is planted, and finally bears fruit much later on when the difficult nature of Zidane&#8217;s memories echoes the turmoil we&#8217;ve known to be growing within Vivi. It&#8217;s a fitting payoff for such a long-term narrative, and answers are delivered in full at a decent pace.</p>
<p>In contrast, as the <b>Kingdom Hearts</b> games rolled on, all subtlety went out the window, and the nature of memory became the focus of the story. Though it&#8217;s probably untruthful to say the games discuss the &#8220;nature of memory&#8221; so much as memories are just weird, malleable plot points. While games like Vagrant Story and Final Fantasy IX ask the player to consider how important our perception of events in the past are to understanding our present selves and the way we are understood by others, games like Kingdom Hearts asks&#8230; similar questions in much less helpful ways, mostly by using terms that don&#8217;t reflect the complexity of the self. According to Wikipedia: &#8220;Roxas is a &#8216;Nobody&#8217;, a being created when the series&#8217; main character Sora briefly lost his heart during the first game of the series.&#8221;</p>
<p>Games such as <b>Valkyrie Profile: Silmeria</b>, the <b>Xeno-</b> series, and&#8230; guh&#8230; <b>The 3rd Birthday</b> all consider memories and identities to be malleable things that can be lobbed around like softballs as major plot points. The thing about having confusing plots heavily focus on character&#8217;s identities shifting and changing is that, after going through all the effort to keep it all straight in my head, <i>the last thing I want to do is think about the nature of memories as they apply to me.</i></p>
<p>A digestible plot and satisfying mechanics keep my reptilian brain happy and occupied while my mammal brain considers the implications of the game&#8217;s message. A complicated plot where I have to spend time drawing parallels between characters&#8217; predicaments and my own is order to make sense of the importance of the proceedings is a waste of brain activity better spent on anything more fulfilling.</p>
<p>Which brings me to <b>Soul Sacrifice</b>, possibly the only game to use malleable memories as a valid plot point.</p>
<p>Soul Sacrifice is a grotesque fairy tale. The premise is simple. You are imprisoned by an evil wizard with plans to sacrifice you when a magical talking journal bound in flesh slides into your cell and tells you that if you read and relive the events of the entries within, you will be able gain the powers of the long-dead sorcerers detailed, learn the nature of your captor, and defeat him.</p>
<p>I say that Soul Sacrifice is a fairy tale because the nebulousness of the world allows for a certain suspension of disbelief. You are told very little, so that when very strange and unlikely things happen, you say to yourself, &#8220;I guess that&#8217;s how things are in this world.&#8221;</p>
<p>This is a world were magic is not clean energy, but more like a nuclear weapon, leaving fallout about to mutate lands and beasts. Magic is an extension of the greed within every living thing, from trees to rats to children. Magic is constantly threatening to make things worse for everyone.</p>
<p>Only state-sanctioned sorcerers are capable of wielding magic safely, paradoxically for the purpose of eradicating the monstrous abominations created by magical radiation. Sorcerers are widely feared and hated as a symbol of violence and degradation, but are the only things keeping people safe.</p>
<p>The way sorcerers in particular are able to deal with monsters is through the art of sacrifice. They absorb the essence of fallen foes (who, in their weakened states, take on the form they once had, whether it be a mangy cat or a wrathful man) and seal it within their right arms. As a rule, sacrificing more foes makes the sorcerer stronger.</p>
<p>In doing this, though, sorcerers also takes some of their target&#8217;s essence into them, their soul, the thing that is the sum of their experiences and feelings.</p>
<p>Absorbing a very powerful, very willful soul can affect the behavior and, YES, the memories of the sorcerer.</p>
<p>But you can save monsters, too. Instead of increasing your attack power through sacrifice, being a savior can boost your life and defensive power, as well as allow you to recruit allies to your cause. However, although saving some monsters can provide certain passive boons when saved, the rewards are often dubious (powers aren&#8217;t as good, allies are dumb), and on the whole (at least according to the game&#8217;s lore) authorities do not tolerate sorcerers acting as saviors, since they are contracted executioners, not judges.</p>
<p>Still, as the one in the field, you have the choice. Every time you fell a monster, you can choose to either save it or sacrifice it.</p>
<p>What&#8217;s great about the story is that rules of a sorcerers duties are set forward very early on. Sorcerers kill monsters, and they sacrifice them, becoming living silos of malice. You take these rules for granted. The game keeps you so focused on killing monsters and getting stronger that, after a while, you don&#8217;t think twice about the nature of what you&#8217;re doing, and the progression of the story becomes secondary to the progression of the challenge. As with any diligent sorcerer, it becomes a numbers game. How many of what kind of monsters do I need to kill to get enough powers to kill that next monster?</p>
<p>By keeping the player focused on the mechanics of play, the game frees itself to influence the player&#8217;s thoughts from behind the scenes, rather than awkwardly confronting them about the game&#8217;s &#8220;point&#8221; via cutscene. In Soul Sacrifice, the mechanics drive the player forward, but they also connect directly to the nature of the story and the plights of the characters. The way that a single decision annihilates all other realities, the way we value or cast aside things based on their usefulness, the ways in which growth may transform us or make us more like who we truly are.</p>
<p>When the game finally reveals its hand &#8211; when the nature of the relationships between the very small cast of characters starts to slide into focus &#8211; that&#8217;s when you finally start to think about the implications of what you&#8217;ve been doing. <i>Not because the game begins navel-gazing and actively discusses the nature of itself, but because you are put in a situation where you can&#8217;t help but wonder what it means.</i></p>
<p>Soul Sacrifice does this in the same way every good game has done it. At the game&#8217;s climax, you are asked to do something you&#8217;ve done a thousand times before, but for an entirely different reason that puts your entire experience up until that point in a different perspective.</p>
<p>And while the ending does indeed come down to a binary decision, I am pleased to inform that neither ending is truly good or bad &#8211; or, well, I didn&#8217;t think so. Though I felt that one ending was, dare I say, more poetic and more in keeping with the tone of the game than the other. Believe or not, this dopey, macabre little game, like a fairy tale, has a very beautiful moral. From the creator, <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/mightyno9/mighty-no-9">Keiji Inafune</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>My own life story has been the inspiration of this game. I was put in a lot of situations where I had to make tough decisions. I learned that things don’t go well just because you want to be famous or rich or a better person. You have to constantly think what you’re willing to give up or sacrifice to make things happen.</p></blockquote>
<p>Sometimes I feel like the importance of a story can be broken down into an equation. <i>(Decisions made</i> x <i>frequency)</i> / <i>time</i> = <i>importance</i>, or something. The more time you spend thinking you understand something only to find how wrong you were always seems to pack an emotional punch, no matter the situation.</p>
<p>Time, however, is also Soul Sacrifice&#8217;s draw back. As glad as I am that I played it, it&#8217;s hard for me to say that it&#8217;s truly a <i>great</i> game because it is exceedingly repetitive. I literally stopped playing for a few months for that reason. Often times you&#8217;ll find yourself asked to do missions very similar to those you&#8217;ve done before with very meager rewards. These rewards do build up over time, but they don&#8217;t feel as essentially fulfilling as other similar kill-thing-and-receive-loot games like Monster Hunter or Dragon&#8217;s Crown.</p>
<p>But, hey, there&#8217;s <a href="http://operationrainfall.com/soul-sacrifice-delta-announced/">a new version</a> coming out. Maybe then I could suggest this game unequivocally. Until then, Soul Sacrifice is probably the best boring game I&#8217;ve played all year.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>So I played Remember Me, and then I stopped.</title>
		<link>/2013/06/19/so-i-played-remember-me-and-then-i-stopped/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Terry]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 18:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false"></guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why is parkour still a thing in video games now? It was a key component in Assassins Creed and Mirror&#8217;s Edge, and it should have stopped there. (I&#8217;ll accept inFamous, too, because at least it&#8217;s fun then.) But, here we are, still climbing up the sides of buildings. Like, EVERYONE can climb the sides of&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="2013/06/19/so-i-played-remember-me-and-then-i-stopped/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">So I played Remember Me, and then I stopped.</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="http://www.digitaltrends.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Remember-Me.jpg" width="600" /></p>
<p>Why is parkour still a thing in video games now? It was a key component in Assassins Creed and Mirror&#8217;s Edge, and it should have stopped there. (I&#8217;ll accept inFamous, too, because at least it&#8217;s fun then.)</p>
<p>But, here we are, still climbing up the sides of buildings. Like, EVERYONE can climb the sides of buildings <i>so easily.</i> Doesn&#8217;t that seem like a really hard thing to do? That didn&#8217;t used to be a thing. In older video games, when we came to a wall we were like, &#8220;Well, I guess we better find a way around it.&#8221; But now everyone&#8217;s trying to just climb over it.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s a cute idea, but you can&#8217;t put that genie back in the bottle. In the old days the question was, &#8220;If I have a grenade launcher, why can&#8217;t I explode that locked door off its hinges?&#8221; Now it&#8217;s, &#8220;If I can climb THAT wall, why can&#8217;t I climb EVERY wall??&#8221; It&#8217;s funny. As aesthetics get more realistic, the occasional inconsistencies with video game verisimilitude become more insufferable.</p>
<p>But then, hey, I guess I shouldn&#8217;t be surprised parkour is so present in a French game. A French sci-fi game. About memories. Called <i>Remember Me</i>.</p>
<p>The Ghost in the Shell series was a very dire and realistic meditation on the nature of technological progress and its influence on politics, the planet, and the self. It&#8217;s a crime drama first, but the themes of memories and identity run throughout all of the proceedings.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Remember Me opens like, &#8220;You lost your memories! Because a company called Memorize decided they could do whatever they wanted with your memories! Now take &#8217;em down, so we can all have our memories back! Even if you have to mess with other people&#8217;s memories! And remember to remember to memorize memories!&#8221;</p>
<p>Now, isn&#8217;t it kind of obvious that the big twist is gonna come when you get your memories back? I know it&#8217;s a sci-fi, but it feels really silly and regressive to just make your plot <i>actually involve</i> what your game is thematically addressing.</p>
<p>Maybe I&#8217;m getting stuck on this, but&#8230; You&#8217;re supposed to use the plot to convey the point, the same way you use a frying pan to cook a steak. You can&#8217;t take the meaning of the game and then build the plot on that. You can&#8217;t cook a steak with another steak.</p>
<p>To be fair, there is other stuff going on in the game: the haves vs. the have-nots. The rich can afford to relive their own happy memories, while the impoverished can only scrape together the memories of others and go nuts in the process. There&#8217;s even a character early on whose decision to do something drastic is based on a very expensive hospital bill she has to pay. It actually feels just barely relevant at times.</p>
<p>But it&#8217;s not just plot and aesthetics you use to convey meaning: it&#8217;s mechanics. The script seems to be telling us that the game is about the malleability of the human psyche, and that my character is a genius hacker. If that&#8217;s so, how come I spend less time rewriting people&#8217;s memories &#8211; which is, in fact, a very neat and juicy bit of the game &#8211; and more time punching junkies and climbing up and down the sides of walls?</p>
<p>The thing is, Remember Me isn&#8217;t the first game that&#8217;s about running toward a glowing waypoint or climbing and punching things like a drunk amnesiac baboon. But it&#8217;s the last one I deign to play.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
